if your trading profits are built on an
illusion it's only a matter of time
before everything crashes down and
that's the hidden mistake I see even
from traders who think they're
profitable you yourself might already be
making profits from your trading but
there's always that nagging question in
the back of your mind is this legit or
am I just on a lucky streak and that
question matters because if it really is
just luck it can vanish in an instant
but if you know for sure that you've got
a genuine Edge it changes everything
you'll handle losses way better you
won't be panicking and tweaking your
strategy every time something goes wrong
because you know that your profitability
will bounce back so in this video I'm
going to show you how to confirm once
and for all whether you genuinely have
an edge or if it's all Just an Illusion
and if you follow what I'm about to
share with you you'll fundamentally
change how you look at every single
trait not only will this help prove if
you do have an edge or not it will help
you to enhance your Edge or even set you
up to actually develop one in the first
place and by the way if you're serious
about developing your trading Edge
you're going to want to check out the
free trading that I've Linked In the
description box down below but more
about that later all right let's dive in
so how do most Traders try to confirm if
they have an edge they'll usually look
at metrics like their profit Factor
Traders equation maybe even just their
overall returns but there's a huge issue
here those measurements just rely on the
results of your trades the profit
profits and losses I mean sure that
sounds logical like why wouldn't you use
p&l data but let me show you an example
to expose why this is so misleading this
is the actual performance of a trading
strategy that generated profits of over
140% that's amazing right steady growth
frequent but small losses seems like
it's a solid risk profile nothing too
adventurous and you know doesn't look
like the account is going to crash and
burn if you plug this into the usual
tools profit Factor Sharp ratio you name
it you'd get the green light that this
strategy has a real Edge but check this
out now you're looking at 200 trading
strategies that are completely random no
Edge at all basically coin flips and
that awesome performance that I showed
you before it's just this line here pure
luck yet most common tools would say yes
this is a profitable trading system keep
doing what you're doing and that's
dangerous because since there's no real
Edge behind that strategy that same
strategy could easily follow a path like
this one in the next 200 trades wiping
out all gains in fact over a long enough
period of time you'd expect it to fall
back to being around break even so then
the question is how do we fix this well
it all comes down to probabilities let's
clear something up what exactly is a
trading Edge when you open a trade
you're basically making a judgment about
probabilities even even if you don't
realize it like for example let's say
that you're planning a trade on WTI oil
you've got your stop loss below these
lows here and a Target at the top here
it's a classic one to2 risk reward setup
if you have no Edge the raw maths says
that there's a 33.3% chance for a profit
and a 66.7% chance for a loss so that's
just break even over a large sample or
actually a loss once you factor in
transaction costs like the spread and so
on so we call those probabilities the
base rate the probability of an
opportunity if you had no Edge at all
but here's the key if you decide to take
that trade you're implicitly stating
that you believe the probability of a
profit is higher than the base rate of
33.3% otherwise why would you be taking
the trade so what this means and I'm
going to really oversimplify things just
to get the points across is that having
a trading Edge doesn't mean being able
to choose which op opportunities are
going to result in a profit it means
being able to estimate the probabilities
of a situation differently to the base
rate and on average be right and if you
are right on average you're going to be
making money and if you're not right you
won't now assuming that you are accurate
with your probability estimates the
further you are from the base rate the
bigger your Edge will be and the more
profits you'll be able to reliably make
so that means if you want to know
whether you do have an edge and how big
that edge is there are two things you
need to measure how far your estimates
are from the base rate and how accurate
those estimates are and if you stay
tuned I'm going to walk you through a
step-by-step way to measure exactly that
just imagine the confidence that you're
going to gain when you know that your
probabilities line up with reality
that's what I want for you so let's get
into the details First Step start making
explicit probability estimates for every
trade if you're not quantifying the
probability of a profitable outcome how
do you know if you're right or not so
open up a new spreadsheet and log the
following columns trade ID base rate
your estimated probability estimated
probability divided by base rate and
then the actual outcome was it a profit
or a loss so it might look something
like this so the estimated probability
divided by base rate which I'll call the
epbr from now on that ratio shows us how
much further your estimate is compared
to the base rate so for example if the
base rate is
33.3% and you estimate 40% your eppr is
1.2 but if you estimated
66.7% your epbr is two so the higher the
number the more aggressively you think
you're beating the base rate probability
which as I mentioned a moment ago is one
aspect of your Edge if you're right with
it listen I know most Traders don't use
probabilities in their trading so most
people watching this won't be using
probabilities most trading Educators
despite saying trading is a game of
probabilities don't teach about it why
because they are just making things up
as they go along they don't really have
any real depth of knowledge or
experience but that's a whole discussion
for another time so if you're not sure
where to start with all of this check
out the free training that's in
description box down below so in that
training I'll start teaching you exactly
what you need to know and I'll even
follow up with more free training
afterwards so it's a real no-brainer go
and check it out the link is down below
now something that you might have been
thinking about is that each individual
trade only has one outcome it's not like
it ends up being a 60% profit and a 40%
loss and therefore your probability
estimate was exactly right it's only one
outcome so we can't directly say whether
your exact probability estimate was spot
on for each individual trade but here's
the trick if we analyze groups of Trades
we can see how accurate you are on
average now I have to give a massive
shout out here to a member of our
community Kento IA he helped us to
refine our original process for these
next steps that I'm going to walk you
through and he helped us to make them a
lot better now this guy is so switched
on when it comes to the data side of
trading and he also helps out other
members of our community with their data
and finding these optimizations and
insight sites and that's really the
benefit of having an amazing Community
with really smart people everyone can
learn and level up so here are the next
steps that you need to follow you're
going to group your trades together
based on the epbr ratio which means
we're grouping them based on how
aggressive our estimates were and you
can group them in other ways as well
which we'll talk about in just a moment
now we can open a new tab in the
spreadsheet and add the following
columns the label for the group in this
case it will be the
epbr the mean average of the base rate
for that group the mean average of the
estimated probabilities the actual
result percentage profitable that is so
we want that as a percentage the sample
size the mean
epbr then the actual results divided by
the mean base rate we can then take this
data and plot it onto a chart so that we
can analyze our performance so we're
going to plot the mean EP PBR and the
actual result divided by the mean base
rate and you can see we've added the
dotted line at one this is Break Even
which means anything above this is
profitable and anything below it is
losing if the actual result divided by
mean base rate is above one that's good
it means you're profiting however just
like we discussed earlier in the video
that could be just pure luck you know
that amazing performance that I showed
you from the completely random trading
strategy would ALS also be above one
overall but it had no Edge so here's
where things get fun your epbr line is
what you expected before entering the
trade and the closer the actual result
line is to this epbr line the more
accurate your estimates were let's put
this into perspective if your results
were profitable for a group of Trades
you'd expect that that days a point for
this line would be above one but if your
epbr line is very far from that it means
that although you were profitable your
estimates and reality were not aligned
so there's a chance that the profits may
have been luck at best we can say that
you do have an edge but the profits are
unreliable and you can't depend on your
performance in future on the other hand
if the estimates and reality are very
close it means your estimates are much
more accurate there's something that
you're reading in the market that allows
you to accurately predict what may
happen next that means your profits are
less likely to be luck and are going to
be more reliable because they're an
accurate reflection of what you
anticipated whatever you're analyzing in
the markets is clearly meaningful but no
one is ever going to be perfectly
accurate with this there will always be
ways to improve whether that's because
you're currently below base rate so
you're losing or you're above base rate
but inaccurate so you want to refine the
skill to make sure you're not trading
just based on luck and this is where
grouping the data in different ways can
help you reveal insights about which
areas you need to work on a bit more you
know at the moment we're grouping the
data based on the epbr that means that
we're seeing how we perform depending on
how ambitious our estimates are so for
example it might be the case for you
that the higher the epbr ratio where
you're further from the base rate the
more overconfident you are and that
might mean that in future you can just
recalibrate because when there's a
higher epbr for an opportunity you just
adjust your estimated probability down a
touch and that's how you recalibrate
then but really this is the fun bit
where you get to really dig deeper into
different ways of categorizing your
trades to find those insights like for
example what if you group The trades
based on different market conditions
different setup types different aspects
of your analysis different times of day
or days of the week the possibilities
are endless and each layer of insight
helps you to refine your approach you
can cut out losing scenarios refine
what's working you might even realize
that your whole trading approach is just
entirely meaningless and you've just
been trading based on luck now that's a
bit of pill to swallow but it's always
better to find that out rather than just
continuing with your head buried in the
sand not knowing whether it's luck or
not so this video is getting on a bit
and you can see it's getting quite dark
in here so let's start wrapping things
up hopefully now you can see how
important this data can be and how the
data that you're currently tracking
probably isn't helping you to improve in
specific ways most measures don't tell
you specific specifically what's working
or what to change they're usually just
vanity metrics but using probabilities
to analyze your performance will show
you exactly where things stand so you
can make logical changes much more
intelligently all right so a couple of
things firstly if you found this helpful
hit the thumbs up button drop a comment
down below and share this with another
Trader that you know let's help more
people wake up to the fact that luck is
not a strategy there are so many Traders
out there who need this training and in
fact many trading mentors and gurus
probably need it the most so be the good
guy and share it with them as well next
check out the link in the description
for my free training that I mentioned
earlier that will get you on the right
track with all of this and start using a
meaningful trading approach that isn't
just based on luck if you're stuck using
outdated methods that the industry just
keeps trying to shove down your throat
this training will open your eyes and
save you loads of time and frustration
and finally remember all of this
probability data is only meaningful if
you've got enough trades in your sample
if one of the groups that you're
analyzing only has a small number of
Trades you can't come to a reliable
conclusion about it so on screen now
you'll see two videos one shows you
exactly how large your sample size needs
to be and we talk about that and the
other is a trading simulator guide that
will help you gather reliable data much
quicker so go and watch those now
because once you've got enough trades
under your belt and you're analyzing
them in the right way you'll never have
to second guess if your profits are real
or just a lucky streak and then you can
optimize your way to success so I'll see
you in one of those videos in a second
but until then trade logically and let's
keep building your Edge